准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
改过自新
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
编剧
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
海之霸
我投降
I surrender
不知道那个小独眼这次有什么诈
I wonder what form of trickery
is up that miniature cyclops' sleeve this time
好了  痞老板
All right, Plankton
虽然我不知道你想怎么整我
I don't know what you're trying to pull on me
但我跟你说  你绝不可能得逞
but I'll tell you right now it ain't gonna work
我没想整你  老螃蟹
There's no pulling, Krabs
没看到我的和平赠礼吗
Can't you see my peace offering?
这是什么
What is this?
太好笑了  痞老板
Very funny, Plankton
但你想欺负我不识字还是嫩了点
But you're gonna have to do a lot better
than taking a stab at my illiteracy to offend me
你不懂吗  老螃蟹
Don't you get it, Krabs?
我放弃
I give up
不想再跟你竞争了
I'm through competing with you
可你之前老是热火朝天地
But what about all those fevered attempts
想尝试偷我蟹黄堡秘方又怎么说
at trying to steal my Krabby Patty recipe?
没错
Exactly
先前那些就只是尝试而已
They've all been just attempts
而且次次都失败得可悲惨了
and every single one a miserable failure
每每想到就感觉自己动脉塞满了焦虑
I can feel my arteries clogging up with anxiety
just thinking about it
给你看点东西
Let me show you something
你看看这地方
Look at this place
你搞什么  痞老板
Crimony, Plankton
你就没听说过大扫除吗
You ever hear of spring cleaning?
又有什么意义
What's the point?
知道上次这边来客人是什么时候吗
Do you know when the last time I had a customer was?
其实我完全不记得你还有过客人
Actually, I can't recall you ever having a customer
客人就是他
Well, there he is
所以我决定彻底退出餐饮业
That's why I've decided
to quit the restaurant business altogether
把海之霸变成
and turn the Chum Bucket into
这个
this
生日快乐
你想把你家餐厅变成垃圾堆吗
You want to turn your restaurant into a pile of junk?
不对
No
这些都是小玩意
These are knickknacks
准备放我新开的礼品店拿来卖
for the new gift shop I'm opening up
你这一定是在开玩笑吧
Come on, this has got to be a joke, right?
我是认真的  老螃蟹
I'm serious, Krabs
海之霸马上就会变成可爱小店
Soon the Chum Bucket will be a nice little store
专门卖小摆设跟泡泡糖
for bric-a-brac and bubblegum
好吧  痞老板
All right, Plankton
但要注意了
but be aware
我绝不会卸下防备心
I'm not letting me guard down
随便你防  前任死对头
Guard away, my ex-enemy
我就待在这创业  不跟你竞争了
I'll just be here
starting my new competition-free career
怎么了  蟹老板
What's going on, Mr. Krabs?
痞老板又编造了个无脑计划
Plankton's concocted another hair-brained scheme
来偷我秘方
to steal me recipe--
所以睁大眼睛看好了
so keep your eyes peeled
剥 开
就听你的  老板
Whatever you say, Cap'n
你这员工真听话
Now, that's an employee who follows orders
那什么怪声
What in blazes is that noise?
海霸店
盛大开业
看看啊
Would you look at that
感觉我会喜欢上
I have a feeling I'm gonna like
售卖新奇小玩意的新生活
this new life of novelty items
好个小聪明  痞老板
Clever, Plankton
你那套我也会
Two can play at this game
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
快看我到海霸店买的酷玩意
look at this cool knickknack I got at the Chumporium
里面一定藏了个话筒或者摄像头
I know there's a microphone or camera in here somewhere
蟹老板  我真的觉得
Mr. Krabs, I really don't think
里面没什么怪东西
there's anything weird in there
等着瞧好了
We'll see about that
把这东西放里面保管得了
I'll just put this in here for safekeeping
听见没  痞老板
You hear, Plankton?
快加入你的旧日好友
Join your other friend from the past
谁都不准看
Now nobody's getting to see anything
你们不懂吗
Don't you understand?
这都是他诡计的一环
This is all part of his ruse--
都是表面工夫
it's just cosmetic
他自以为能造假骗到我们
He thinks he can fake us out
但我们要给他点厉害
But we'll show him
要比那个造假的还会造假
We're gonna out-fake the faker
看来痞老板真的不来偷秘方了
Well, it looks like old Plankton's
really going through with it
这下再也用不着担心他了
I guess we don't have to worry about him anymore
没错  这回可把他给折磨惨了
Yep, we sure whipped him this time
小子们  已经确认安全了
Okay, boys, the coast is clear
痞老板已经改过自新了
Plankton's turned over a new leaf
真是好消息  蟹老板
That's some good news, Mr. Krabs
确实  你这小白痴
It sure is, you little half-wit
知道还有什么好消息吗
And you know what else is good news?
终于可以用那部DJ机了
We can finally use that deejay system
奏乐  海绵宝宝
Hit it, SpongeBob
马上来  老板
Right away, sir
狂欢吧
Let's party
我赢了
I won
快来跳舞
It's time to boogie
太傻了吧
This is idiotic
不跳舞就开除你
Dance or you're fired
没问题  蟹老板
You got it, Mr. Krabs
你说怎么样啊  你这小
How do you like them apples, you little
走吧  兄弟
Come on, buddy
一起睡一觉
let's get some shut-eye
海霸礼品店马上要迎来重要一天了
We've got a big day ahead of us
at the Chumporium Gift Shop
等一下
Wait a minute
怎么
What the?
雪花球
毛绒玩具
货架
Store shelves?
新奇玩具
Novelty toys?
熔岩灯
Lava lamps?
没用的小玩意
Useless knickknacks?
很有说服力
Very convincin'
但我还是不信
but I'm still not buying it
你想要战斗吗  痞老板
You want a battle, Plankton?
那我就给你战争
I'm gonna give you a war
雪花玻璃球得干净了才会快乐
A clean snow globe is a happy snow globe
痞老板
Plankton
虽然你骗得过别人
You may have fooled everyone else
还骗得过你自己
you might have even fooled yourself
但就是骗不过我
but you ain't foolin' me
我懂了
I get it--
你把我抓了个正着
you caught me red-handed
往日时光真美好  对吧尤金
Those were the days, huh, Eugene?
但我发现生活中
But I found there was more to life
比偷你秘方更有意义的事多着呢
than just trying to steal your formula
而在这卖新奇玩意正好有意义
I found it all right here, in novelty items
放屁
Bupkes
尤金啊
Oh, Eugene
顽固不化
stuck in your old ways
放屁
Bupkes
这世上有这么一件事非常确定
If there's one thing that is certain in this world
那就是你肯定忍不住想要我秘方
it's that you can't resist me formula
你一定很想要吧
You know you want it
谢了
Thanks
但我不要
but no
我就知道
I knew it
一直都是你想骗我交出
It was all a trick to get me to hand over me
等等
Wait
你刚刚是说
Did you say
不要
no?
你要是不信我
Well, if you don't believe me
那也是你的问题  不关我事
that's your problem, not mine
问题
Problem?
我没问题
I don't have a problem
你才有问题
You're the one with the problem
看看这个
Look at this
毫无意义
It means nothing
都是假象
It's all a facade
恶作剧
A hoax
诡计
A con
掩饰
A front
虚伪
A sham
诱骗
A snow job
胡说八道瞎扯淡
Baloney with a side of flimflam
里面必有阴谋
and an order of jive
看吧
See?
谁才有问题呢
Who's the one with the problem?
看看
Look
你干了什么好事
what you've done
这可是我的生计
This is my livelihood
没错
Sure it is
这秘方你可想要了吧
And this isn't the formula that you don't want
来拿啊
Come on, eh?
太慢了
Too slow
快
Get
滚
out
我懂了
I get it
假装不被秘方动摇  赢取大家信任
Stick to your guns and eventually we'll all believe it
让大家卸下防备  然后趁大家不注意
Soften us up, then when our backs are turned
你就要动手耍诈了
you make your move
这是什么
What's this?
秘方
老螃蟹
Hey, Krabs
怎么了
What?
我就知道你会回来
I knew you'd come back
你忘了样东西
You forgot something
你就不懂吗
Can't you understand
我都浪费了这么多时间追着你跑
I've wasted so much time chasing after you
现在总算有样属于我的东西了
and now I have something that's mine
而且还让我
And it makes me
很快乐
happy
想不到真的会有这一天
I never thought I'd see the day
从前认识的那位无脊椎动物怎么了
What happened to the invertebrate I used to know?
痞老板
Plankton
来了来了
Coming, coming
痞老板
Plankton?
尤金
Eugene?
听我说
Listen, uh
我只是想
I just wanted to
就是
you know
为我今天的所作所为道歉
apologize for my behavior today
先前做了一堆错事  然后
Wasn't right what I done, and
我发现我伤害了某位的感情
and I realized I hurt the feelings of, uh
他是
of, uh
我非常关心的一位
someone I care about
你还在听吗
You still there?
对
Yeah
我还在听
I'm still here
好
Good
我想要补偿你
I want to make it up to you
要不要来杯汽水
What do you say we grab a soda?
好啊
Sure
蟹堡王
汽水
很高兴你能来  兄弟
Glad you could make it, buddy
所以
So
有什么事  老螃蟹
what's this about, Krabs?
我觉得既然不再是死对头了
I thought that since we're no longer archenemies
不然就
maybe
不然我们可以
maybe we can
从头来过
start over?
好
Yes
好  我可想从头来过了
Yes, I would like that very much
看来我赢了
I guess I won
信任亭
这样不好吧  痞老板
I don't know about this, Plankton
没事  往后摔就对了
Come on, just fall back
相信我  我会接住你的
Trust me, I'll catch you
刚刚真是太神了  痞老板老兄弟
That was truly amazing, Plank, old buddy
我真的能百分百信任你
I guess I really can trust you 100%
谢了  尤金
Thanks, Eugene
刚刚
That
真的对我意义重大
means a lot to me
为了向你证明我多信任你
And just to prove it to you
请你收下一点心意
I want you to have something
不用了
No, no
真是的  不用礼物的
come on, now, no gifts
不对
No, no
我是请你收下这个
I want you to have this
是我的秘密配方
It's me secret formula
你居然会这么想
I can't believe you would even think
但现在情况不同了
But things are different now
说真的  这样对我意义很重大
Honestly, it would mean a lot to me
你
You
你是认真的
you're serious
尤金  我收下你给的秘方
Eugene, if I take this formula from you now
总会有那么几分不信任感
there will always be a hint of doubt
没事  收下吧
Come on, take it
你确定吗
You sure?
生活真美好  老螃蟹
Life is good, Krabs
没错  兄弟
Sure is, buddy
没错
Sure is
好耶  宝贝
Yeah, baby
到手了
This is it
好耶
Yeah
到手了
I got it
我邪恶又缜密的阴谋成功了
My diabolical, extremely convoluted plan worked
我早该去当政客的
I should have been a politician
骗到你了
老螃蟹
我才不会给你秘方呢
I'd never give you the formula
我装得更缜密  把你给骗到了
I fooled you with an even more convoluted charade
一朝被蜗咬
分镜总监
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
好个阳光明媚的一天
What a sun-tastic day
蜗牛黏液
Snail trail
那个海绵宝宝得管好他家宠物
That SpongeBob needs to keep his pet
别让它进我庭院
out of my yard
清理它留的脏东西可烦死我了
I am sick of cleaning up after him
不能弄脏我的宠物石头收藏啊
Not my pet rock collection
够了
That's it
你都已经不止一次
This isn't the first time
拿你恶心的分泌物弄脏我家庭院了
you've soiled my yard with your revolting excretions
但是给我记好了
But mark this down in your little notebook
以后你再也没法得逞了
It will be the last time
这种多刺的廉价木头连小蜗都拦得住
This cheap splintery wood will keep even Gary out
现在舒坦多了
Now I feel safe
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
嗨  章鱼哥
Hi, Squidward
海绵宝宝
Hey, SpongeBob
把你家死蜗牛赶出我家地盘
Keep your shell vermin off of my property
我这位烦人黄色邻居  再有下次
Then next time, my annoyingly yellow neighbor
你家宠物又把黏液涂满我庭院
your wet pet oozes on my lawn
我就只能呼叫抓蜗牛大队了
you'll leave me no choice but to call snail control
那个小怪物
That little monster
还咬我
He bit me
小蜗
Gary
不行  小脏孩
No, dirty boy
你平常不这样的
This isn't like you
平常这样的都是你  海绵宝宝
But it's just like you, SpongeBob
养了这么一只贱蜗牛
to raise such a misbehaved mollusk
小蜗才不贱
Gary's not misbehaved
它貌似是有哪里不舒服
But there does appear to be something wrong with him
确实
I'll say
希望它打过疫苗了
I hope he's had his shots
当然打过
Of course
疫苗全都打了吗
All of his shots?
没错
Affirmatory
狂犬病呢
For rabies?
打了
Yep
蜗痘还有软壳舞蹈症呢
Snail pox and soft shell dance?
打了
Yupie
囊炎呢  巨大肿包呢
Bagitis, lumpy-bump trump
青春焦虑症呢
teen angst?
都打了
Yep, yep, yep
别忘了最严重的病
Let's not forget the worst of them all
疯狂蜗牛症
Mad snail disease
你是说你家宠物
You mean your pet
没打过疯狂蜗牛症疫苗吗
hasn't been vaccinated for mad snail disease?
疹子好像已经开始长起来了
Looks like the rash has already started
疹子
Rash?
说说看  你喉咙疼不疼
Tell me, do you have any soreness of throat?
既然你这么一说
Well, now that you mention it
我喉咙真有点干
my throat is a little dry
这个症会毁坏你的身体
This disease will ravage your body
让你眼睛充血  失去平衡
with bloodshot eyes, loss of balance
裤子凌乱
messy pants
胸腔发痒
ticklish rib cage
脚趾甲极度不整
severely untrimmed toenails
最后  一旦被患病的蜗牛咬到
and finally, the bite from that infected snail
你就会变成
will turn you into
丧尸
A zombie
你得把你家蜗牛送去看医生
You need to get that snail of yours to a doctor
免得它咬了什么重要人物
before he bites someone important
疯狂蜗牛跑走了
There's a mad snail on the loose
小蜗
Gary?
疯狂蜗牛要来了
The mad snail is coming
一旦被咬到  就会变丧尸
If he bites you, you'll turn into a zombie
天啊  那疯子什么毛病
Jeepers, what's with all the lunatics?
亲爱的  你看
Look, honey
它真的太可爱了
isn't he the cutest?
过来吧  小朋友
Come here, little buddy
它好可爱
He's just adorable
真的有疯狂蜗牛症
Mad snail disease is real
我是丧尸
I'm a zombie
我被疯狂蜗牛咬到了
I've been bitten by a mad snail
我得了疯狂蜗牛症
I've got mad snail disease
那我也得了
Then I've got it
刚有只蜗牛也咬了我
A snail just bit me, too
现在插播爆炸新闻
We interrupt this program to bring you a news blast
请稍候
爆炸新闻
壳中恐慌
刚刚收到的消息
This just in
恐慌与疾病正在迅速蔓延
Fear and disease is spreading like wildfire
起因是一只杀手蜗牛
as a killer snail has been
咬到了裤头村的居民们
biting the denizens of Bikini Bottom
使其感染了
Infecting them with
疯狂蜗牛症
普通老百姓通常会这么描述病情
Ask any old fish on the street and they'll tell you
病菌会从咬伤处进入
that germs enter through the bite radius
一路逆流而上
Traveling upstream
直至全身都充满了
until the entire host body is full of
疯狂蜗牛症
现在为大家
We now take you
现场连线新闻快报记者帕奇帕金斯
to Action News Reporter Perch Perkins
live on the scene
我是帕奇帕金斯
Perch Perkins here
正在采访本次疫情的首位感染者
with the first victim of this epidemic
说说看  章鱼哥先生
Tell me, Mr. Tentacles
你从什么时候开始怀疑
when did you first begin to suspect
自己变成丧尸的
you were a zombie?
一开始有只疯狂蜗牛咬了我
Well, after I was bitten by a mad snail
我起了疹子
I began to get a rash
然后又失去了平衡  胸腔又发痒
Followed by loss of balance, ticklish rib cage
还有其他一些症状
and a few other symptoms
有只蜗牛咬了我
I was bitten by a snail
感觉我有点失去平衡了
I kind of feel off balance
我胸腔也发痒了
I have ticklish ribs, too
但我又没被咬到
And I haven't even been bitten
不好了  病菌会通过空气传播了
Oh, no, it's spreading through the air
最新独家消息
Well, you heard it here first
我们就快要惨死了
We're all doomed to a horrible demise
都怪某只犯病蜗牛
thanks to a diseased snail
小蜗
Gary?
那只可爱又黏黏的蜗牛
I can't believe that sweet and slimy snail
居然会造成这么大破坏
would cause all this destruction
我是丧尸
I'm a zombie
要来吃你软绵绵的黄肉
here to dine on your squishy yellow flesh
蟹堡王
锁上了
It's locked
放我进去啊
Somebody let me in
海绵宝宝  快点进来
SpongeBob, come in, boy
也带你朋友进来
And bring your friends in, too
样子还挺饿的
They look hungry
住手
Stop
谁都不准放进来
You can't let anyone in
可他们就只是想吃蟹黄堡而已
But they just want to dine on some krabby patties
他们是丧尸
They're zombies
只想吃我们的肉
They only want to dine on our flesh
好吧  蟹黄堡钱从你工资扣
All right, but it's coming out of your paycheck
我又没在这上班
I don't work here
可是蟹老板  是我海绵宝宝啊
But, Mr. Krabs, it's me SpongeBob
又要怎么知道你没变成
But how do we know you haven't become
那种吃肉怪物呢
one of those voracious flesh-eaters?
吃肉怪物能这样吗
Could a voracious flesh-eater do this?
海绵宝宝  真的是你
SpongeBob, it's you
没错
That's right
放我进去  省得我被吃掉
so let me in before I'm eaten
没错  就是海绵宝宝
Yeah, that's SpongeBob all right
是这样吗
Or is it?
那可不见得真的是海绵宝宝
I don't believe that's the real SpongeBob
样子非常丧尸化
He looks pretty zombie-fied
你看他脸色有多黄
Just look at how yellow he is
拜托  派大星
Come on, Patrick
丧尸会往钱包放好朋友的照片吗
would a zombie have a picture
of his best buddy in his wallet?
一辈子好朋友
多半不会
Perhaps not
但我会把眼睛放你身上盯着你
But I've got my eye on you
如果你能拔了眼睛放他身上
If you could pull out your eye and put it on him
那你该不会
wouldn't that make you
也变丧尸了吧
a zombie, too?
你说得对
You're right
我变丧尸了
I'm a zombie
谁敢说我们都没变丧尸
Who's to say we're not all zombies?
那只蜗牛
The snail
小蜗
Gary
你没事吧  兄弟
Are you okay, buddy?
快点过来
Come here, boy
千万别靠近它
No, don't get near it
太可怜了
The pity of it all
我不敢看
I can't watch
大家都说你是怪物
All those people think you're a monster
但在我心里  你只是一只蜗牛
but I know you're just a snail
小蜗
Gary
你怎么能这样
how could you?
海绵宝宝被自己养的蜗牛感染了
SpongeBob's been infected by his own pet snail
太讽刺了
The irony
快  得隔离那只带病蜗牛
Quick, we must quarantine that infected snail
免得它把剩下的裤头村居民全咬了
before he bites every last Bikini Bottomite
抓住那只蜗牛
Let's get that snail
好
Yeah
千万别伤害小蜗
No, don't hurt him
交出蜗牛
Hand over the snail
都是为了它好  海绵宝宝
It's for his own good, SpongeBob
我绝对不会让你们碰小蜗
No, I won't let you touch Gary
理智点吧
Stop the madness, man
疯狂蜗牛症现在就要结束
The mad snail disease ends now
抓住蜗牛
Seize the snail
慢着
Halt
有谁说到疯狂蜗牛症吗
Did someone say mad snail disease?
就因为这个大惊小怪吗
Is that what all this fuss is about?
对啊
Yeah
你哪来的懂哥
What do you know about it?
你问得还真巧
Funny you should ask
先自我介绍一下
Allow me to introduce myself
吉尔吉利安医生
Dr. Gill Gilliam
蜗疾家及蜗家
S.D.E. + S.E.
"S.D.E. + S.E."?
蜗牛疾病专家及蜗牛专家
Snail disease expert and snail expert
很遗憾要给大家透露这个事实
I'm sorry to break this to you all
你们所谓的疯狂蜗牛症
but that "mad snail disease" you're talking about
根本不存在
it doesn't exist
没错  没这回事
That's right, no such thing
就只是个上古都市传说  是谣传
It's an old urban legend, a myth
所以说我们不是丧尸了
Well, does that mean we're not zombies?
当然不是
Of course not
谁都不是丧尸
No one is
就只是群体歇斯底里
It's just mass hysteria
可我脚趾甲严重不整又是
But what about my severely untrimmed?
你这只是一般的不整而已
Those are only moderately untrimmed
所有所谓的症状都只是常见的小病
All the supposed symptoms are just common ailments
不要激动
Easy, boy
可小蜗又是怎么回事
But what about Gary then?
要是它没得病
If he doesn't have a disease
怎么会把大家都咬了  连我都咬
why'd he bite all those people including me?
问题就出在这里
The problems right here
它的脚上扎了一根小刺
He's got a little splinter in his foot
这一定就是它产生瘟热的原因
I'm sure this was causing him distemper
进而出现严重的发脾气症状
Making for serious grouchy snailitis
小蜗  我就知道你没病
Oh, Gary, I knew you weren't disease-ridden
你还爱我吗
Do you still love me?
小蜗恢复正常了
Good old Gary's back
章鱼哥
Hey, Squidward
你不是丧尸  记得吗
you're not a zombie, remember?
我就是
Yes, I am
欢迎光临蟹堡王
Welcome to the Krusty Krab
需要点餐吗
May I take your order?
问题解决  皆大欢喜
All's well that ends well